<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Helm on Atharva CJ's place</title><link>https://acjoshi.dev/tags/helm/</link><description>Recent content in Helm on Atharva CJ's place</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 02:14:25 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://acjoshi.dev/tags/helm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Getting started with OIDC and Dex with kind</title><link>https://acjoshi.dev/post/getting-started-with-oidc/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 18:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://acjoshi.dev/post/getting-started-with-oidc/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>this article covers how you can setup a local cluster in with kind (not rudely), the next one would cover GitHub Oauth process.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="oidcintro">OIDC?(Intro)&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Open IDentity Connect is a AUTHENTICATION protocol that is built on top of Oauth2.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Oauth2 is primarily a AUTHORIZATION protocol.(The capitalization is more a reminder to myself than the reader)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>OIDC is the reason why you get that shiny &amp;ldquo;Sign in with Google&amp;rdquo; or Microsoft, or Facebook button in different applications you see.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="why-do-i-need-dex">Why do I need dex?&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Imagine this you have built your cool application and it has a standard login page that accepts email and password. But its 2025 now and you feel you need to ease the process by having a google sign in button.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>So you set out on a journey to implement google Oauth2 by going to google console, registering your app, getting your client id and secret and start using it for your app.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Luck is on your side and your application is growing popular, now you want to on onboard facebook users. But oh no!! your application is hard coded with google endpoints for authentication, so you pile up some technical debt and hardcode your facebook endpoint.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>As days pass you realise you maybe need Microsoft Oauth as well, and you finally realise maybe it was a bad idea to hard code facebook Oauth2, as your authentication endpoints keep increasing and it becomes a hassle to maintain dev,stage, and prod credentials of your application.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-dex">What is Dex?&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://dexidp.io/">dex&lt;/a> is an open source project that aims to simplify authentication for applications.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Imagine this, you only had to deal with OIDC once (Ideally never would be nice, but its never ideal is it) and someone else took care of every other OIDC providers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dex would talk to other OIDC providers and your application remains agnostic about the different providers, your application only knows about Dex and the tokens Dex gives.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dex comes with a local installation too, which means that the source of truth for authentication is its own database, you can interact with this service via grpc calls.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You can configure the storage options as described &lt;a href="https://dexidp.io/docs/configuration/storage/">here&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Oauth2 is the only protocol your application needs to support, the upstream connector can be anything, LDAP,SAML,OAUTH,here&amp;rsquo;s the exhaustive &lt;a href="https://dexidp.io/docs/connectors/">list&lt;/a>.
Connector is basically the place where Dex will go to for getting the user credentials verified.
So your app only has to implement OIDC process for Dex, Dex will take care of the rest.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="but-what-is-oidc-technically">But what is OIDC, technically?&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>before i summarise briefly how an OIDC flow looks like, lets get on the same page about terminology for clarity.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>